A Guide to the Executive Papers of Governor Benjamin Harrison, 1781-1784
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Executive Papers of Governor Benjamin Harrison, 1781-1784
The Library of Virginia
44660
7.75 cubic feet
Virginia Governor (1781-1784: Harrison)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Acquired prior to 1905.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm - Miscellaneous Reel 2970-2980.
Miscellaneous Reel 2970 - 1781 Nov. 30-1782 Jan. 23
Miscellaneous Reel 2971 - 1782 Jan. 24-Apr. 16
Miscellaneous Reel 2972 - 1782 Apr. 16-June 15
Miscellaneous Reel 2973 - 1782 June 16-Aug. 23
Miscellaneous Reel 2974 - 1782 Aug. 24-Oct. 29
Miscellaneous Reel 2975 - 1782 Oct. 29-Dec. 27
Miscellaneous Reel 2976 - 1782 Dec. 28-1783 Mar. 23
Miscellaneous Reel 2977 - 1783 Mar. 24-June 25
Miscellaneous Reel 2978 - 1783 June 26-Nov. 27
Miscellaneous Reel 2979 - 1783 Nov. 28-1784 June 7
Miscellaneous Reel 2980 - 1784 June 8-Nov. 30
Biographical Information
Benjamin Harrison was born on 5 April 1726 at Berkeley Plantation in Charles City County, Virginia. Harrison was the son of Benjamin Harrison and Anne Carter Harrison. He attended the College of William and Mary in 1745, but did not complete his studies. He entered the House of Burgesses in 1748 and served until 1775. He represented Charles City County in the First through Third Virginia Revolutionary Conventions. A delegate to the First & Second Continental Congress, Harrison was chairman of the Committee of the Whole House and a signer of the Declaration of Independence. Harrison resigned his seat on the Continental Congress in 1778. He was also elected to the Virginia House of Delegates in 1776 serving as speaker of that body from 1778 until his election as governor in 1781. Harrison served three one-year terms as governor from 1781 to 1784 and returned to the House of Delegates after his term ended. He was a member of the House of Delegates until his death 24 April 1791. Harrison married Elizabeth Bassett and had 7 children, including William Henry Harrison (1773-1841) who was the ninth president of the United States.
Scope and Content
Governor Benjamin Harrison's Executive papers are organized chronologically with undated items arranged at the rear of the collection. These papers consist of incoming correspondence and drafts of outgoing correspondence during Harrison's three one-year terms as governor of Virginia between 30 November 1781 and 30 November 1784. The correspondence primarily relates to the Revolutionary War, peace with Great Britain, relations with Native Americans, the boundary between Virginia & Pennsylvania, the cession of western lands, the Public Jail, arms, ammunition, and the militia. In addition to correspondence, there are accounts, bonds, certificates, commissions, reports, receipts, proclamations, appointments, resolutions of the Continental Congress & the Virginia House of Delegates, acts, orders, depositions, petitions, recommendations, returns, and other sundry items.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Executive Papers of Governor Benjamin Harrison, 1781-1784
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Palmer, William P., ed., CALENDAR OF VIRGINIA STATE PAPERS, 1652-1781, Vol I, and 1782-1784, VOL. II, Richmond: R. F. Walker, Printer, 1875.
Contents List
- Executive Papers of Governor Benjamin Harrison, 1781-1784., Extent: 19 boxes. (Box 1-19)
  Noteworthy correspondence originates from the United States government, Virginia state government, Governors from other states, and miscellaneous sources. Prominent correspondents from the United States government include John Hanson, Elias Boudinot, & Thomas Mifflin, Presidents of the Continental Congress; Charles Thomson, Secretary of Congress; Benjamin Lincoln, Secretary of War; Robert Morris, Superintendent of Finance; Robert R. Livingston, Secretary of Foreign Affairs; and James Madison, Jr., Edmund Randolph, Joseph Jones, Arthur Lee, James Innes, John F. Mercer, James Monroe, Samuel Hardy, Thomas Jefferson, & Theodorick Bland, Virginia's delegates in the Continental Congress.
  John Hanson, President of the Continental Congress transmits several acts and ordinances of the Continental Congress. Notable are the following: ordinance for amending the ordinance ascertaining what captures on water shall be lawful (1782 Jan. 8); act recommending the several legislatures to establish a speedy mode of administering justice between French & U.S. citizens (1782 Jan. 27); ordinance for further amending the ordinance ascertaining what captures on water shall be lawful (1782 Feb. 26); resolution that the states immediately send delegates to Congress (1782 May 28); and a resolution that it be recommended to the several states to suppress all traffic between their respective citizens & the enemy (1782 June 24). Hanson was succeeded as President by Elias Boudinot in November 1782. Boudinot encloses proceedings of a meeting of the corporation of Annapolis regarding the proposition to Congress on the subject of the permanent residence of Congress in Maryland (1783 June 10). Boudinot also encloses a copy of a letter from George Washington regarding the pay of the Army and the settlement of accounts (incl. letter of William Heath to Washington) (1783 June 20). On 22 July 1783, Boudinot encloses a proposition of the New Jersey Assembly to provide a place for the permanent seat of government in their state. Boudinot's successor Thomas Mifflin writes from Annapolis on 20 December 1783 enclosing a copy of an act of Congress regarding the act of Virginia ceding territory in the west to the U.S. Mifflin also writes regarding problems with finances (1784 Apr. 1).
  As Secretary to the Continental Congress, Charles Thomson often transmits resolutions of that body to the governor. Of note are the following: resolution that the legislature of each state raise a quota of men assigned to each state (1781 Dec. 10); resolution that the Superintendent of Finance provide a contract for supplying the recruits from the places of rendezvous until they join the army (1781 Dec. 19); resolution that the several legislators provide by law for the establishment of a speedy mode of administering justice between French citizens & U.S. citizens and for vesting persons on the sea coast with power to secure shipwrecked property (1782 Jan. 25); resolution that the legislatures of the respective states be recommended to authorize & empower the U.S. in Congress in the final settlement of the proportions by each state of the general expenses of the war (1781 Feb. 20); resolution recommending that the legislatures of the several states to make a suitable provision for staying all suits by individuals against officers & servants for debts contracted by them for supplies furnished or services rendered to the U.S. (1782 Mar. 19); resolution that it be recommended to the several states to take effectual measures to prevent any persons from harboring, secreting, etc., any prisoner of war taken from the enemy (1782 Mar. 30); resolution authorizing the executives of the several states in certain cases to suspend the commissions of captains of private armed vessels (1782 May 23); resolution that members of Congress who are deputed to repair to the Southern States be authorized to make such expenditures to the legislature of Virginia (1782 May 30); resolution directing an arrangement of the Virginia Line (1782 Aug. 7); resolution that Virginia continue a garrison at either Yorktown or Gloucester (1782 Aug. 27); resolution that the U.S. will not enter into the discussion of any overtures for pacification, but in confidence and in concert with his most Christian Majesty (1782 Oct. 4); resolution regarding the number of lieutenants assigned to each regiment of infantry, the reporting of sick & wounded soldiers by the Inspector General, the retirement of junior lieutenants, & commissions issued to all officers who were appointed by their respective states (1782 Oct. 16); resolution that the U.S. accept all right, title, interest, jurisdiction, & claim of the state of New York (1782 Oct. 30); resolution that the Superintendent of Finance be directed to instruct the commissioner appointed to settle the accounts of the State of Virginia with the U.S. to receive such proofs as shall be exhibited to him (1783 Feb. 10); resolution that the state legislature obtain a just & accurate account of the quantity of land in the state, granted or surveyed for any person (1783 Apr. 18); resolution re. the report of the committee on the Virginia cession of the lands north west of the Ohio River (1783 Sept. 13); resolution devising means for a full representation (1783 Nov. 1); resolution recommending to the several states measures looking to the restitution of all confiscated estates belonging to real British subjects, etc., and allowing persons of any other description to go to any parts of the U.S., and to remain one year to obtain restitution of such estates (1784 Jan. 14); resolution that the several states be requested to annually appoint their delegates to serve in Congress for one year (1784 Mar. 23); resolution recommending each state be represented by three members in Congress (1784 Apr. 19); resolution for states to issue a reward for the arrest of Longchamps for the accused assault & battery upon M. Mabois, Consul of France (1784 May 29); and a resolution that the several states be credited their accounts with the U.S. for the specie value of all sums paid to their officers & soldiers in the Continental army (1784 June 1). In addition, Thomas writes the various state legislatures recommending a census of white inhabitants to be transmitted to Congress (1781 Dec. 11). Finally, Thomson writes regarding the election of Elias Boudinot as president of Congress (1782 Nov. 4).
  Benjamin Lincoln, Secretary of War, transmits a resolution of Congress that the state of Pennsylvania & Virginia order 150 men to Fort Pitt (1782 Aug. 9). Lincoln also writes to Nathanael Greene regarding Gen. George Washington's letter concerning the removal of troops for the winter, the merger of Virginia cavalry regiments, & a request to form all continental troops into proper corps (1782 Sept. 30). Lincoln's assistant secretary, William Jackson encloses a copy of the agreement entered into by the commissioners appointed to settle an exchange of prisoners of war in the Southern Department (includes a list of officers captured who were not exchanged) (1783 Jan. 20). Jackson writes Robert Morris on 19 February 1783 regarding the continuance of recruits of the Virginia Line and a contact for Winchester. Later, Lincoln writes regarding the parole of Lt. George Dunlap, a British prisoner of war (1783 Mar. 12). Lincoln also writes concerning the following: authority for Lt. Lawson to continue in the service in place of Lt. Vandevall who is retiring (1783 Mar. 31); dispute in rank between Captains Hopkins & Swan (1783 Mar. 31); and the appointment of Col. Hawes as inspector to the Virginia Line (1783 July 26).
  Superintendent of Finance, Robert Morris, corresponds often with Governor Harrison respecting various economic matters. On 21 Dec. 1781, Morris requests the laws of the state and minutes of the legislature. Morris also encloses a letter to the states of Massachusetts, Rhode Island, & Maryland regarding their non-compliance of the recommendation of Congress for an impost of five percent on goods imported, prizes, & prize goods (1782 Jan. 3). Later, Morris transmits an ordinance incorporating subscribers to the Bank of North America (1782 Jan. 8). Additionally, Morris writes regarding the following: copies of letters to David Ross, Commissioner of Trade, regarding goods purchased from traders at Yorktown & British traders at Yorktown (1782 Jan. 11); credit from France, Spain, & Holland and the assistance of state legislatures in continuing supplies to Continental forces (1782 Feb. 9); a specific tax on tobacco (1782 Feb. 26); an act of Congress that the state of Virginia furnish the men & beef required by Gen. Nathanael Greene (1782 Feb. 28); the acts of Congress for settling the finally adjusting all the public accounts (1782 Mar. 9); resolutions of Congress that that the state legislatures authorize & empower the U.S. in the final settlement of the proportions to be borne by each state of the general expenses of the war through 1 January 1782 (1782 Apr. 5); a contract entered into by him on behalf of the U.S. to produce a relief to the American prisoners in New York (1782 Apr. 10); supplies for the state of Virginia from the Minister Plenipotentiary of France (1782 Apr. 27); payments to officers who are to expend the public money in bank notes (1782 Apr. 30); nomination of Zephaniah Turner as commissioner to settle the accounts between the state of Virginia & the U.S. (1782 May 21); the approbation of Zephaniah Turner as the commissioner for settling the accounts of Virginia (1782 July 2); an act to authorize the U.S. in Congress in the final settlement of the proportion to be borne by the state of New Jersey (1782 July 9); the state's practice of making partial payments to their troops, as well as expending monies for the purchase of clothing (1782 July 29); the need for the states to support the war effort (1782 July 30); a resolution of Congress that Virginia continue a garrison at either Yorktown or Gloucester at the expense of the U.S. (1782 Aug. 30); a resolution of Congress that $1,200,000 be assessed on the states for payment of the interest of the public debt (incl. correspondence to President of Congress, Order of Congress, & resolution) (1782 Sept. 12); a resolution of Congress that the commissioners appointed to settle the accounts of the several states be directed to examine, receive, & destroy so much of the Continental money as may be in the state treasuries not exceeding the quota fixed by the Act of Congress (1782 Sept. 20); an act of Congress that the New Jersey Legislature be informed that Congress has adopted every means for securing payment of the arrears due to the Army prior to 1 January (1782 Oct. 5); delays in supplying the Public Treasury (1782 Oct. 21); resolutions of Congress regarding the requisition made from the several states of two million dollars (1782 Oct. 23); articles of clothing in France belonging to the state of Virginia (1782 Oct. 23); a request that the Pay Master be furnished with an account of the payments & advances which have been made by the states to any officers or soldiers if the American Army (1783 Mar. 20); a letter of Benjamin Franklin re. a loan from France, peace, & credit abroad (1783 Mar. 25); the order of Congress recalling all cruisers commissioned by them (1783 Mar. 25); a state of receipts & expenditures for the years 1781 & 1782 (1783 Apr. 7); acts of Congress re. his continuance in office until arrangements for the reduction of the Army can be made & that the respective states be called upon to forward the collection of taxes (1783 May 12); an act of Pennsylvania for the settlement of public accounts (1783 May 20); a report of a committee of Congress to examine into the conduct of the office of Finance (1783 June 21); a state of the receipt & expenditures of public monies from warrants between 1 January & 30 June 1783 (1783 July 11); the expenses of feeding the troops from Carolina (1783 July 15); copies of accounts of public officers (1783 July 16); a letter from Daniel Parker, N.Y., giving account of forgeries (1783 July 21); the operation of the Office of Finance and the financial future of the nation (incl. letter of Elias Boudinot) (1783 July 28); a extract of a letter from Joseph Pennell, Commissioner for Accounts of the Marine Department, re. the recommendation of Congress to empower the commissioners to recover from individuals debts due & effects belonging to the U.S. (1784 May 26); and the retirement of the present commissioner for settling the accounts of Virginia with the U.S. and nominating Andrew Dunscomb (1784 Oct. 19).
  Robert R. Livingston, Secretary of Foreign Affairs, writes Governor Harrison to keep him informed of events in Europe. In his letter of 19 February 1782, Livingston writes regarding recent events affecting France, Spain, & Holland. Afterward, Livingston encloses a resolution of Congress to make a confidential communication to the several states in regard to the intelligence received through his office (1782 May 2). Livingston also writes concerning the following subjects: the birth of the dauphin of France (1782 May 14); a resolution of Congress that the Secretary of Foreign Affairs obtain authentic returns of the slaves & other property carried off or destroyed in the course of the war by the enemy for the Minister Plenipotentiary negotiating a peace (1782 Sept. 12); the appointment of John Adams as Minister Plenipotentiary of the U.S. (1782 Sept. 15); an abstract of the preliminary articles for a general peace signed on 20 January 1783 (1783 Mar. 24); and a proclamation of Congress declaring the cession of arms between the U.S. & Britain (1783 Apr. 12).
  Virginia's delegates in the Continental Congress including James Madison, Jr., Edmund Randolph, Joseph Jones, Arthur Lee, James Innes, John F. Mercer, James Monroe, Samuel Hardy, Thomas Jefferson, & Theodorick Bland, communicated frequently with the governor concerning supplies, military intelligence, news from abroad, and peace with Great Britain. Significant correspondence includes the following: complaints of the performance of David Ross in providing supplies and recommending John Cowper as his replacement (1781 Dec. 4); intelligence from New York regarding the embarkation of troops (1782 Jan. 1); the memorial of Daniel Murray asking for pay for his services in the Illinois country (1782 Jan. 8); Gov. Alexander Martin, North Carolina, encl. a proclamation making provision for the arrest of certain plunderers who carried off slaves & other property belonging to citizens of North Carolina & Virginia (1782 Feb. 6); support for Gen. Nathanael Greene, the success of Count de Grasse in the West Indies, & the movements of Adm. Hood (1782 Feb. 15); the settlement of public accounts from the commencement of the war through 1 January 1782 (1782 Feb. 25); intelligence from the West Indies (1782 Mar. 5); a supply of beef required from Virginia for the Southern Army (1782 Mar. 12); advice of Europe of the determination of the British Cabinet to continue the war and France & Spain's reinforcements to the West Indies (1782 Mar. 26); resolutions of Congress recommending to the states to pass laws giving a reward of eight dollars to any person who shall apprehend & safely secure any prisoner of war taken from the enemy (1782 Apr. 2); cipher prepared for the correspondence between the executive & delegates in Virginia (1782 Apr. 22); payments made by the states in the new Continental bills, stores belonging to Virginia, & preliminary articles of peace (in French) (1782 Apr. 23); the thinness of the military ranks & intelligence from Europe & the West Indies (1782 Apr. 30); commissions for armed vessels, the lack of agreement between opposing parties of the enemy for peace, the capture of the garrison at Minorca by the Spanish, & the renewal of the siege of Gibraltar (1782 May 7); actions of the French & English fleets in the West Indies (1782 May 28); naval operations in the West Indies, transport of supplies from the French, Count Beniousky's proposals to furnish three legions of foreign troops, & intelligence of enemy movements in New York (incl. copies of letters of Gen. George Washington, Count Beniousky, etc.) (1782 June 4); rejection of Count Beniousky's proposal (1782 June 18); establishing connections between the U.S. & various European nations and illicit trade between New York & the enemy (1782 June 25); intelligence from Europe & New York (1782 July 2); lack of intelligence regarding the fleets in the West Indies (1782 July 9); supplies requested by the French, the seizure of British goods, & a report from New York that the enemy have evacuated & burnt Charleston and sent the garrison to the West Indies (1782 July 16); the superintendent's contract for the main army (1782 July 23); the arrival of French ships in the Chesapeake (1782 July 30); the letter of Benjamin Lincoln, War Office, re. the removal of Continental stores from Yorktown to the head of Elk (1782 Aug. 13); negotiations for a general peace at Paris, the proposition of British commanders for an exchange of their seamen for their soldiers, and the embarkation of the enemy from New York & Charleston (1782 Aug. 19); the arrival of prisoners from England including forty from Virginia (1782 Aug. 31); confiscations, restitution of slaves by the British commander, & Washington's movements in New York (1782 Sept. 10); intelligence transmitted by Gen. Washington & an extract from the proceedings of Congress concerning cession of western lands (1782 Oct. 1); the plenipotentiary commission issued to Mr. Fitzherbert by George III & a memorial of Simon Nathan asking for relief for large amounts advanced to Col. Clark & Todd (1782 Oct. 22); William Hay encl. an inventory of goods on hand belonging to the state (1782 Nov. 6); Jaquelin Ambler, Treasury Office, transmitting a general list of the commutable articles received at the Treasury under the revenue law (1782 Nov. 9); acts of Congress re. the reduction of the Army and news from Gen. Washington of the evacuation of Charleston (1782 Nov. 26); the sale of powder from the magazines of the U.S., lead mines, & arms from France (1782 Dec. 3); a resolution of Congress that the Superintendent of Finance be directed to represent to the state legislatures of the several states the necessity for their complying with the requisitions of Congress for raising $1,200,000 (1782 Dec. 6); relief of prisoners from Canada on their way to Virginia (1782 Dec. 17); Virginia's repeal of her law imposing a duty of five percent on imported articles & prize goods (1782 Dec. 31); the settlement of Simon Nathan's claim (1783 Jan. 21 & 28); arbitration with Simon Nathan (1783 Feb. 4); the King's speech to Parliament & resolutions that the Superintendent of Finance be directed to instruct the commissioner appointed to settle the accounts of Virginia with the U.S. to receive such proofs (1783 Feb. 18); peace with Great Britain (1783 Mar. 11); preliminary articles of peace, including independence, boundaries, fisheries, confiscated property, commercial privileges, & evacuation of military posts (1783 Mar. 12); the results of negotiations in Europe (1783 Mar. 24); rejection of propositions for a cessation of hostilities to Sir Guy Carleton & Adm. Robert Digby on account of a lack of authority from their court (1783 Apr. 1); New York's offer of a tract of land in Kingston for the use of Congress & their suggestion of a tract in Georgetown on the Potomac River (incl. broadside with preliminary articles of peace between Britain, France, & Spain) (1783 Apr. 10); Congress's recommendation to the states for vesting in them the power to create a revenue adequate to the funding of the public debt & the arrangement with Sir Guy Carleton for getting possession of posts occupied by the British in the U.S. (1783 Apr. 22); the acceptance of a cession of territory to the U.S. by Virginia (1783 Apr. 29); John Wormeley's request for permission to return to his wife & family (1783 Apr. 29); mutiny among troops in Philadelphia (1783 June 24); resolutions of Congress that the Secretary of War dispatch a force to suppress the mutinous soldiers (1783 July 5); forgers of treasury notes in New York (1783 Aug. 1); the commission to settle the accounts of the state with the U.S. & the refusal of the Empress of Russia to receive the American minister (1783 Aug. 14); orders to Sir Guy Carleton to evacuate New York & the delay in the signing of the definitive treaty with Great Britain (1783 Aug. 23); a settlement on the Muskingum, the return of Baron von Steuben from the Northwestern frontier, & the evacuation of New York (1783 Sept. 8); resolutions of Congress that Virginia keep up two armed vessels for the defense of trade & twenty-five privates with proper officers to guard the public prisons & stores (1783 Oct. 4); resolutions of Congress respecting their permanent & temporary residence (incl. report on Indian affairs) (1783 Nov. 1); credentials of Peter John Van Berkel, Minister Plenipotentiary (1783 Nov. 1); the claim of Oliver Pollock (1784 Jan. 23); petition of the inhabitants of Kentucky to be erected into a separate state & taken into the Union (1784 Feb. 20); the act for Western cession, payments made & arrears still due by the states on the requisition of 1781 October 30, & the ratification of the definitive treaty (1784 Mar. 3); claims of the Indiana Company and the jurisdiction of Virginia courts over the western lands (1784 Mar. 12); Benjamin Franklin's letter re. the British court (1784 Mar. 18); an exemplification of the deed of cession (1784 Mar. 22); the running of the boundary line between Pennsylvania & Virginia (1784 Apr. 10); a report of the grand committee on the requisition for the current year and objections to the plan for paying interest on the national debt (1784 Apr. 10); sending Jefferson to Philadelphia or Ft. Pitt (1784 Apr. 23); the possibility of Jefferson accepting the appointment as a commissioner for extending the boundary line between Virginia & Pennsylvania and the cession of the western territory by Virginia (1784 Apr. 30); the act of Congress on the subject of the western territory and the estimate & requisitions of Congress (1784 Apr. 30); the removal of Congress to New Jersey & Maryland, commercial treaties with the maritime powers of Europe & Africa, & the plan for the purchase of the western territory (1784 May 13); the negotiation of commerce treaties abroad, the appointment of John Jay as Minister of Foreign Affairs, & the requisitions on the states (1784 May 14); a letter of Mr. Ellicott of Maryland accepting an appointment to run the boundary between Pennsylvania & Virginia (1784 June 11); a letter from the ministers in Europe re. orders to exchange the ratification of the definitive treaty (1784 July 17); news of the ratification of the definitive treaty (1784 July 20); the state of Indian affairs in the Western frontier, the appointment of commissioners to treat with the Indians, & the settlement of lands westward of the Ohio before the treaty is complete (1784 Aug. 3); progress in collection members of Congress after their removal to Philadelphia (1784 Sept. 16); a new commission & the evacuation of the posts on the North West frontier (1784 Oct. 20); the lack of a quorum in Congress, speculation on who will be appointed president, & war between the Emperor & the United Netherlands (1784 Nov. 7); and the formation of a Congress, the election of a president, & the act of Connecticut authorizing Congress to carry the impost into effect when twelve states have adopted it (1784 Nov. 29).